Guide to the Edward Burne-Jones Letters to Cormell Price
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Edward Burne-Jones Letters to Cormell Price
1852-1862
MSS 45
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
.42
1 box
This collection comprises 16 items, including 15 letters from Sir Edward Coley Burne-Jones and Cormell Price and 1 autograph envelope from Burne-Jones addressed to Price. The correspondence was written over the course of a decade, between 1852 and 1862. The letters are indicative of Burne-Jones and Price's long and close friendship and are very affectionate and personal in nature. The letters are rich in detail, with Burne-Jones sharing news of mutual friends, his Oxford lessons, his social life and his artistic and literary endeavors.
Biographical / Historical
Sir Edward Coley Burne-Jones (1833-1898) was a British painter, illustrator and designer. Born in Birmingham in 1833, Ruskin studied at the Birmingham School of Art from 1848 to 1852, before going on to read theology at Exeter College, Oxford, in 1853. At Oxford, Burne-Jones was a key figure of what became known as the Birmingham Set, a group of Oxford students who hailed from Birmingham or who had, as Burne-Jones did, attended King Edward's School, Birmingham. The group were hugely influential in Britain's visual art scene in the mid-nineteenth century and its members Burne-Jones, William Morris and Charles Faulkner were founding members of Morris, Marshall, Faulkner and Co., a company manufacturing furnishings and decorative art, in 1861. Burne-Jones is closely associated with the later phase of the group known as the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood. The Pre-Raphaelites sought to reform British art through a return to honest simplicity and the use of luminous colors and literary themes. Burne-Jones deviated from the earlier Pre-Raphaelites in his alignment with the Aestheticism movement which burgeoned throughout the latter half of the nineteenth century and which advocated for an appreciation of art's aesthetic beauty for its own sake rather than for the social-political themes of its subject matter. Alongside other artists associated with the Pre-Raphaelites, including Dante Gabriel Rossetti, Burne-Jones was a contributor to the Oxford and Cambridge Magazine. Burne-Jones produced many artistic works, in a variety of media including stained glass, watercolors, oils, and tapestries.
The recipient of the letters, Cormell Price (1835-1910), was one of Burne-Jones's closest friends from their days at King Edward's School, Birmingham. Price attended Oxford two years later than Burne-Jones and, as these letters demonstrate, his decision to apply was very much encouraged by his old school friend. Price studied medicine at the Radcliffe Infirmary under Henry W. Acland (an Oxford physician and close friend of John Ruskin) before going on to tutor the son of a Russian aristocratic, with whose family he travelled around Europe. After returning to Britain, Price went into teaching, becoming the Head of the Modern Side at Haileybury College and Headmaster of the United Services College at Westward Ho! where his nephew, Rudyard Kipling, would eventually become his pupil.
Burne-Jones and Price met as schoolboys at King Edward's School, Birmingham. The two remained very close friends throughout their lives which is evident from the affectionate correspondence present in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Fund.
Arrangement
The letters are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Contents
This collection comprises 16 items, including 15 letters from Sir Edward Coley Burne-Jones and Cormell Price and 1 autograph envelope from Burne-Jones addressed to Price. The correspondence was written over the course of a decade, between 1852 and 1862. The letters are indicative of Burne-Jones and Price's long and close friendship and are very affectionate and personal in nature. The letters are rich in detail, with Burne-Jones sharing news of mutual friends, his Oxford lessons, his social life and his artistic and literary endeavors.
The collection gives an account of the early activities of what came to be known as "The Birmingham Set" and Burne-Jones's letters frequently refer to many of the group's members, including William Morris (often affectionately dubbed "Topsy"), William Fulton, Charles Faulkner, Richard Watson Dixon, Edwin Hatch and Harry MacDonald. The close friendship held between Burne-Jones, Price and the wider group is evident in a letter dated May 18th, 1856, in which Burne-Jones sketches for Price a heart surrounded by the names of their friends, including many members of the Birmingham Set.
The early publishing and exhibition activities of the group are recounted in Burne-Jones's letters. The first letter in the collection, dated January 24, 1852, describes Burne-Jones's agitation to receive articles from Price and Charles Faulkner for a forthcoming publication, perhaps a precursor to The Oxford and Cambridge Magazine. Discussion of The Oxford and Cambridge Magazine also features prominently in the correspondence. In one letter (circa 1856 January), Burne-Jones instructs Price to send him a piece of writing for a forthcoming issue while also lamenting the scandal caused by the January issue's article on the work of Charles Kingsley, a university professor, historian, social reformer, novelist and Church of England priest. The letter goes on to state that William Morris has passed editorship of the magazine on to William Fulford, which Burne-Jones remarks is a "great relief" to Morris.
The post-university activities of the Birmingham Set are also presented in the correspondence. Burne-Jones's letter of June 28, 1861, announces the foundation of Morris, Marshall, Faulkner & Co. by Burne-Jones, William Morris, P.P. Marshall, Ford Madox Brown, Philip Webb and Dante Gabriel Rossetti. The letter describes the company's products as "stained glass, furniture, jewelry, decorations and pictures" and notes that the organization has received many commissions in the short time since its inception.
Also evident in the collection is Edward Burne-Jones and The Birmingham Set's place within the wider literary and artistic circles of mid-nineteenth century Britain. The letters often demonstrate Burne-Jones's connection and friendship with prominent figures of the era. For instance, in his letter dated January 24, 1852, Burne-Jones expounds, at great length, upon his love of the influential art critic, John Ruskin, and his delight in receiving a letter from Ruskin, an event which Burne-Jones claims has transformed him into "a reformed character." Later letters reveal a closeness with a variety of artists, patrons and writers. Burne-Jones's letter of June 21, 1861, provides a particularly detailed account of the lives of a variety of such figures. In it, Burne-Jones describes the stillborn birth of a child of Elizabeth Siddal and Dante Gabriel Rossetti, the death of the Pre-Raphaelite art collector, Thomas Plint, the death of Elizabeth Barrett Browning, and the marriage of Valentine Cameron "Val" Prinsep.
The letters abound with contemporary cultural references and accounts of major events in Victorian society. Burne-Jones expresses, at length, his deep love of the poetry of Alfred, Lord Tennyson, who he describes as "save Shakespeare only […] the only guide worth following far to dream-land." In the same letter, Burne-Jones warns Price that he should avoid seeing Chevalier Count George Jones's "mangling" of Shakespeare and, in another, recommends the work of Edgar Allan Poe (see May 1 and October 29, 1853). The letters also give details about major public events, including the Tooley Street Fire in London and the Victorian superstitions surrounding the Great Comet of 1861 (see June 28, 1861).
The collection chronicles some of the political and academic history of Oxford University in the early to mid-1850s. In a letter dated March 5, 1853, Burne-Jones describes the employment and promotions of various Oxford professors and chaplains and how they relate to the philosophical and ecclesiastical debates of the Oxford Movement. Later, in his encouragement of Price's application to study at the university, Burne-Jones gives long descriptions about Oxford fellowships and scholarships and how to write "Oxford Latin" (see February 28, 1854).
The long and close friendship between Burne-Jones and Price is reflected in the personal and quotidian events about which Burne-Jones writes to his friend. He sends Price a lengthy description of his infant son's features and personality and the health and happiness of his family(see February 23, 1862). The letters are full of details and references to Burne-Jones's father, aunt, friends, social life and the romantic exploits of his and Price's mutual acquaintances. In one letter, he gives Price an hour-by-hour account of his holiday in the River Wye area. (see January 24, 1852).
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1852 January 24; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 2 folded sheets (8 pages): autograph letter signed; each sheet 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Burne-Jones jokingly chastises Price for his last "skinny" letter and promises that "now [he]'ll be revenged" in his response. Burne-Jones describes at length how he spends his time in the River Wye area, which he says is like "Elysium." He describes his daily routine of walking in the countryside, reading and going to the cathedral. He says in his time in the area he has "endured two" parties and complains about the questioning he receives from guests, commenting "girls are such -- hm -- hang 'em they do quiz so, and I [Burne-Jones] make such a capital subject." Burne-Jones asks Price how he is finding reading "Fasti" but admits that he himself has begun the book. He states that, on the "urgent orders of [sic] eminent physician," he is returning home in the next week. He asks his friend if he might see him upon his arrival at Worcester. Burne-Jones ends his letter: "I would have sent you a long illustrated letter, if you had behaved like a gentleman to me, but as it is: good bye." In a postscript, he notes "Oh I have fallen in with such cant, but thank heavens I am still alive, aren't [?] you glad - eating sweetmeats till you burst."
  In an additional sheet, Burne-Jones asks Price to visit Faulkner and draws for Price "an illustration to his article." The drawing is titled "Faulkner's Improved Sewerage" and depicts a set of many bottles and instruments connected to an underground pipe. Burne-Jones admits that he was "in a fearful state" about his writing. He tells Price that he has received a letter response from "the greatest man alive" [John Ruskin] and says that since receiving the missive he is "a reformed character, [he is] not Ted anymore" but "E.C.B Jones," the "man who wrote to Ruskin and got an answer by return.". He declares that he can "better draw [his] feelings" and sketches Ruskin as a saint at whose feet a figure -- perhaps Burne-Jones himself -- is prostrate. He also draws a pig, captioned "THE MAN etc. as before". He ends by sending his good wishes to Price's family and enquiring after the "pretty hand" which addressed the envelope of Price's last letter.
  General
  Addressed from "Land of Caradoc, Banks of the Wye."
  References: Harrison & Waters, page 7; Georgiana Burne-Jones, v. 1, pages 63-64.
  Wye, River, Valley (Wales and England); Correspondence; Pen and ink drawings; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; Faulkner, Charles Joseph, 1833-1892; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1853 March 5; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 23 x37 cm, folded to 23 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Burne-Jones opens by observing that, "like Mahomet of old", Price "finding the mountain won't come to [him]" has "gone to the mountain" and written to Burne-Jones. He offers Price a "free pardon" for not having done so earlier. Burne-Jones accepts Price's congratulations on the "issue of my 'little go'" but notes his tardiness.
  Burne-Jones writes that "your condolence ... on Sewell's leaving is pathetic" noting that it is likely that Sewell will be promoted to rector upon the incumbent's death. This is perhaps a reference to William Sewell, a tutor at Exeter College, Oxford.
  Burne-Jones affirms to Price that he has no plans to move and asks him to relay this information to "the Birmingham people through the medium of the press or in any other more convenient way."
  He asks Price to tell "him" (an unidentified man) that his "reproachful language" insulted Burne-Jones deeply and that Burne-Jones "yearns" for him and will write to him soon. He notes that he pities "Miller" and writes that "Latimer [perhaps the minister at St Paul's, Birmingham] has my good word ... it will help him to make a stand against the uncircumcised." Burne-Jones asks Price if he knows why Hook [i.e., Walter Farquhar Hook?] has been elected to Lincoln instead of Jackson and remarks that he could tell Price "a few truths about Hook that would make [him] sing another tune." Burne-Jones disagrees with Price that Sewell and Gresley will be bishops, claiming that having seen "a little more of the world" than Price has been enough to "disenchant a good deal of [his] grander notions." Burne-Jones notes that he and William Fulford, Charles Faulkner and Richard Watson Dixon talk of little besides these ecclesiastical politics.
  Burne-Jones ends by confirming that he will see Price in two weeks times and sends his kind remembrances to Price's sister and their old school friends.
  Addressed from Oxford. Addressed to Price (on outer leaf) at King Edward's School, Birmingham. With one penny stamp and wax seal.
  Correspondence; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; Dixon, Richard Watson, 1833-1900; Faulkner, Charles Joseph, 1833-1892; Fulford, William, -1897; Hook, Walter Farquhar, 1798-1875; Sewell, William, 1804-1874
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1853 May 1; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 23 x37 cm, folded to 23 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Burne-Jones congratulates Price on his "dutiful and exemplary" conduct, developed "for many years under [Burne-Jones's] auspices." He adds: "it gives me encouragement that the philosophical notions I have inculcated, and wh. have brought such fruits in you, will be equally productive in others." However, so that Price is not "unduly puffed-up," Burne-Jones goes on to jovially criticize Price's "volatile, hurry-scurry, hyper-condensed" writing style.
  Burne-Jones comments that he is glad that he and Price share a similar taste in poetry, noting that "if Tennyson affords you as many hours of unmitigated happiness -- I speak without affection here -- as he has to me, you will look with gratitude to any who helped you to appreciate him -- when I take up the works of any other poet, save Shakespeare only, I seem to have fallen from the only guide worth following far to dream-land." He goes on at length to describe the ways in which poets capture unexpressable emotion, referencing Friedrich von Schlegel's term "sighing after the Infinite."
  Burne-Jones notes that he has devoted hours to contemplating Tennyson's "Tears, Idle Tears." He answers Price's question about Tennyson's "Locksley Hall," stating that the term "gleams" refers to the curlews in the poem. Burne-Jones recommends the work of the poet Alexander Smith, stating that "his writing is almost incomparable, although his aim is evidently more subjective and metaphysical."
  Burne-Jones describes a visit from his uncle. He goes on to give Price an account of their mutual friends. Burne-Jones remarks that he has been amusing himself by pouring basins of water on the crowd below the window. He warns Price that if the Chevalier Count George Jones ever tours Birmingham, he should not go to see him perform on account of his "mangling" of Shakespeare. Burne-Jones tells Price that he is relying on him to join him in founding a "Brotherhood" of which Sir Galahad is to be patron and that he has already enlisted somebody for the order.
  Addressed from Oxford. Addressed to Price (on outer leaf) "to be left at Mr. Jones'," 11 Bennetts' Hill, Birmingham. With one penny stamp and wax seal. With cross writing, pages 1-2. Signed: "Yours, old buffer, for ever, Ted, General of the order of Sir Galahad"
  References: Harrison & Waters, p. 10; Georgiana Burnes Jones, v.1, p. p. 76-79
  English poetry; Correspondence; Galahad (Legendary character); Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892; Smith, Alexander, 1830?-1867; Jones, George, 1810-1879; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1853 August 5; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 envelope: autograph envelope; 7 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Autograph envelope from Edward Burne-Jones, addressed to Cormell Price. *** come back to this *** add letter content ***
  Date from postmark. Addressed, on separate envelope, to "Cormel Price Esqre., R. Price Esqre., Broadway, Worcestershire."
  Without accompanying letter.
  Correspondence; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1853 October 29; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 2 folded sheets (8 pages): autograph letter signed; each sheet 23 x 37 cm, folded to 23 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Burne-Jones expresses his delight upon receiving Price's last letter. He regrets that he cannot respond to Price's latest request on account of being very busy. He also remarks that the subject proposed by Price is "really beyond me." It seems that Price's request is related to a specific poet (perhaps Tennyson, who is discussed at length in the previous letter), for Burne-Jones writes that: "I have not found a day without reading or hearing his work - it is unfair I know to other poets, for he is not a compendium of all that is beautiful, but I take a pleasure in forgetting others, and concentrating myself, for a while, on him alone."
  He congratulates Price upon his ideas, saying that they are "very laudable and worthy of all success." Burne-Jones says he has been reading Edgar Allan Poe's "book of horrors," remarking that although the appeal of his work is shortlived, for the moment, Poe is "lord of the ascendant." He reccommends a number of Poe's stories to Price.
  Burne-Jones asks if Price has read Archdeacon Robert Wilberforce's "Holy Eucharist", describing the book as "the most controversial & truly theological work that has come out for ages."
  Burne-Jones theorizes on public opinion, claiming that "the multitude is moved by passion & feeling and not reason, therefore you must impel them by Rhetoric before you can convince them by logic" and advises Price that "it can't do [Price] any harm to take every possible occasion to perfect [himself] in the noble art of Dialectic." Burne-Jones states that all men argue logically by nature and that the study of Logic is simply "the science of the processes of thought." He tells Price that in the present moment they must "think highly of [their] species, to dream of development, and the Divinity of mind" and states that man "born in free will" is "more independent than angels, for they cannot see by reason, knowing all things by intuition."
  Addressed from "Greater Coll." Addressed to Price (on outer leaf) at Classical Department, King Edward's School, Birmingham. With one penny stamp and wax seal.
  Rhetoric; Correspondence; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892; Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849; Wilberforce, Robert Isaac, 1802-1857
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1853 November 8; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 23 x37 cm, folded to 23 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Burne-Jones tells Price that he must write a letter to "Harry" (Henry Macdonald), but, not knowing Harry's address, must send it via Price.
  Burne-Jones commiserates with Price regarding "the suppression of the Press" which Burne-Jones declares an "act of high-treason against the Great Republic of Literature," "Inquisatorial in a land that acknowledges no Inquisition" and "tyranny." He quotes Tennyson, assuring Price that "the tyrant's cruel glee forces on the freer hour."
  Burne-Jones goes on to describe ecclesiastical rows regarding a position at Exeter College or Oxford University, which possibly revolves around the Oxford Movement. (Burne-Jones writes that: "Hook by the by is to be Bishop of Oxford" which could be a reference to Walter Hook. Hook was educated at Oxford but never became bishop of the city.)
  Burne-Jones concludes by describing a "profound & exhaustive" sermon by Edward Bouverie Pusey.
  Addressed from "Exeter Coll." Addressed to Price (on outer leaf) at "8. Sun St. West, Birmingham." With one penny stamp and wax seal.
  Freedom of the press; Correspondence; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; Macdonald, Henry James, 1835-1891; Hook, Walter Farquhar, 1798-1875
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1854 February 28; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 23 x 37 cm, folded to 23 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Burne-Jones responds to Price's questions about scholarships, noting that the competition for Oxford scholarships "depend entirely upon the men who present themselves for candidacy" and that the University's reputation for "stiffness" deters individuals from applying and so "competition has been less." He tells Price that the scholarships for Queen's College are generous but that the college has changed from "old times." He notes Magdalen College's demyship scholarship form and states that he believes recipients often become full Fellows.
  Burne-Jones gives his friend advice on studying "Oxford Latin," remarking that the "accuracy of translator ... to render the meaning of a passage as plainly" as possible is paramount. He states that "Tacitus [?] is better than Cicero" and that participles are "supposed to be connecting links between sentences etc -- not meaningless nonsense for filling up, to be translated at random by 'forsooth', 'but', 'indeed' etc."
  Addressed from "Exeter Coll." Addressed to Price (on outer leaf) at "Classical Department, King Edward's School, Birmingham." With one penny stamp and wax seal.
  References: Georgiana Burne-Jones, v. 1, p. 98
  Correspondence; Latin language -- Study and teaching; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; University of Oxford
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1854 March 9; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 23 x 37 cm, folded to 23 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 8)